tel: +8619910031394 | jiez@pku.edu.cn

Dr. Jie Zhang is currently an assistant professor of the school of Computer Science at Peking University, China. He is engaged in the research and design of storage systems, non-volatile memory and specialized processors. His research addresses the requirements for high-performance storage systems in the era of big data and artificial intelligence from the perspective of computer architecture. He is dedicated to breaking through the bottlenecks of data migration and the limitations of memory walls in the Von Neumann architecture. The projects he leads and have participated in have been funded by the U.S. Department of Energy, the U.S. Natural Science Foundation, the Korea Natural Science Foundation, Samsung Electronics, SK Hynix, Texas Instruments, and Western Digital with a cumulative total of over 4 million dollars. He has published over 40 papers in top-tier conferences and journals and 22 papers as the first author, including ISCA (two papers), OSDI, HPCA (seven papers), MICRO (two papers), FAST, DAC, Eurosys, PACT, TPDS and TACO.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Peking University, Beijing, ChinaAssistant Professor, PhD advisorSchool of Computer scienceJuly 2021 – CurrentKAIST, Daejeon, KoreaPostdoctoral ResearcherElectrical Engineering (Computing Division)March 2020 – May 2021

EDUCATION

Yonsei University, Incheon, Korea

PhD in Engineering

University of Texas at Dallas, Richardson, Texas

PhD in Computer Engineering (transfer to Korea)

University of Texas at Dallas, Richardson, Texas

University of Texas at Dallas, Richardson, Texas

Master of Science in Electrical Engineering

Nanjing University of Posts and Telecommunications, Nanjing, China

Advisor: Dr. Myoungsoo Jung

BS in Communication Engineering (computer communication) September 2008 – July 2012

PUBLICATIONS

| | 2024 |
|----------------|--|
| НРСА | StreamPIM: Streaming Matrix Computation in Racetrack Memory |
| Top Conference | Yuda An, Yunxiao Tang, Shushu Yi, Li Peng, Xlurui Pan, Guangyu Sun, Zhaochu Luo, Qiao Li, Jie Zhang |
| | IEEE International Symposium on High-Performance Computer Architecture |
| НРСА | BeaconGNN: Large-Scale GNN Acceleration with Asynchronous In-Storage Computing |
| Top Conference | Yuyue Wang, Xiurui Pan, Yuda An, Jie Zhang , Glenn Reinman |
| | IEEE International Symposium on High-Performance Computer Architecture |
| НРСА | LearnedFTL: A Learning-based Page-level FTL for Reducing Double Reads in Flash-based |
| Top Conference | SSDs |
| | Shengzhe Wang, Zihang Lin, Suzhen Wu, Hong Jiang, Jie Zhang, Bo Mao |
| | IEEE International Symposium on High-Performance Computer Architecture |
| НРСА | Midas Touch: Invalid-Data Assisted Reliability and Performance Boost for 3D High- |

tel: +8619910031394|jiez@pku.edu.cn

Top Conference Density Flash

QiaoLi, Hongyang Dang, Zheng Wan, Congming Gao, Min Ye, **Jie Zhang**, Tei-Wei Kuo, Chun

Jason Xue

IEEE International Symposium on High-Performance Computer Architecture

2023

NVMW Optimizations of Linux Software RAID System for Next-Generation Storage

Shushu Yi, Yanning Yang, Yunxiao Tang, Zixuan Zhou, Junzhe Li, Yue Chen, Myoungsoo Jung,

Jie Zhang,

The 14th Annual Non-volatile Memories Workshop

SAC BcBench: Exploring Throughput Processor Designs based on Blockchain Benchmarking

Xiurui Pan, Yue Chen, Shushu Yi, Jie Zhang,

The 38th ACM/SIGAPP Symposium on Applied Computing

CAL Intelligent SSD Firmware for Zero-Overhead Journaling

SCI Journal Hanyeoreum Bae, Donghyun Gouk, Seungjun Lee, Jiseon Kim, Sungjoon Koh, Jie Zhang, and

Myoungsoo Jung,

IEEE Computer Architecture Letters (CAL)

2022

HotStorage ScalaRAID: Optimizing Linux Software RAID System for Next-Generation Storage

Shushu Yi, Yanning Yang, Yunxiao Tang, Zixuan Zhou, Junzhe Li, Yue Chen, Myoungsoo Jung,

Jie Zhang,

14th USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Storage and File Systems (HotStorage 22)

THPC Survey on Storage-Accelerator Data Movement

Zixuan Zhou, Shushu Yi, Jie Zhang,

CCF Transaction on High Performance Computing

NVMW Integrating New Photonic-Based Heterogeneous Memory into Throughput Accelerators

Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung,

The 13th Annual Non-volatile Memories Workshop

NVMW HAMS: Hardware Automated Memory-over-Storage for Large-scale Memory Expansion

Jie Zhang, Miryeong Kwon, Donghyun Gouk, Sungjoon Koh, Nam Sung Kim,

Mahmut Taylan Kandemir, Myoungsoo Jung

The 13th Annual Non-volatile Memories Workshop

2021

MICRO Ohm-GPU: Integrating New Optical Network and Heterogeneous Memory into GPU

Top Conference Multi-Processors (to appear)

Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung,

The 54th Annual IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture

tel: +8619910031394|jiez@pku.edu.cn

ISCA Revamping Storage Class Memory with Hardware Automated Memory-Over-Storage

Top Conference Solution (to appear)

Jie Zhang, Miryeong Kwon, Donghyun Gouk, Sungjoon Koh, Nam Sung Kim,

Mahmut Kandemir, Myoungsoo Jung,

The IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Computer Architecture

NVMW Architecting Throughput Processors with New Flash (to appear)

Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung,

The 12th Annual Non-volatile Memories Workshop

NVMW DRAM-less Accelerator for Energy Efficient Data Processing (to appear)

Jie Zhang, Gyuyoung Park, David Donofrio, John Shalf, Myoungsoo Jung

The 12th Annual Non-volatile Memories Workshop

NVMW Manycore-Based Scalable SSD Architecture Towards One and More Million IOPS

(to appear)

Jie Zhang, Miryeong Kwon, Michael Swift, Myoungsoo Jung,

The 12th Annual Non-volatile Memories Workshop

2020

ISCA ZnG: Architecting GPU Multi-Processors with New Flash for Scalable Data Analysis

Top Conference Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung,

The IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Computer Architecture

FAST Scalable Parallel Flash Firmware for Many-core Architectures

Top Conference Jie Zhang, Miryeong Kwon, Michael Swift, Myoungsoo Jung,

The 18th USENIX Conference on File and Storage Technologies

HPCA DRAM-less: Hardware Acceleration of Data Processing with New Memory

Top Conference Jie Zhang, Gyuyoung Park, David Donofrio, John Shalf, Myoungsoo Jung

26th IEEE International Symposium on High-Performance Computer Architecture

ISPASS Data Direct I/O Characterization for Future I/O System Exploration

Major Conference Mohammad Alian, Yifan Yuan, Jie Zhang, Ren Wang, Myoungsoo Jung, Nam Sung Kim

The IEEE International Symposium on Performance Analysis of Systems and Software

CAL FastDrain: Removing Page Victimization Overheads in NVMe Storage Stack

SCI Journal Jie Zhang, Miryeong Kwon, Sanghyun Han, Nam Sung Kim, Mahmut Kandemir and

Myoungsoo Jung

IEEE Computer Architecture Letters (CAL)

2019

HPCA FUSE: Fusing STT-MRAM into GPUs to Alleviate Off-Chip Memory Access Overheads

tel: +8619910031394 | jiez@pku.edu.cn

Top Conference Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung, Mahmut Kandemir,

25th IEEE International Symposium on High-Performance Computer Architecture

IISWC Faster than Flash: An In-Depth Study of System Challenges for Emerging Ultra-Low

Major Conference Latency SSDs

Sungjoon Koh, Junkyeok Jang, Changrim Lee, Miryeong Kwon, Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo

Jung,

The 2019 IEEE International Symposium on Workload Characterization

DAC FlashGPU: Placing New Flash Next to GPU Cores

Top Conference Jie Zhang, Miryeong Kwon, Hyojong Kim, Hyesoon Kim, Myoungsoo Jung,

The 56th Design Automation Conference (DAC), 2019

TPDS Exploring Fault-Tolerant Erasure Codes for Scalable All-Flash Array Clusters

Top Journal Sungjoon Koh, **Jie Zhang**, Miryeong Kwon, Jungyeon Yoon, David Donofrio, Nam Sung Kim,

Myoungsoo Jung,

IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems (TPDS)

NVMW Addressing Fast-Detrapping for Reliable 3D NAND Flash Design

Mustafa Shihab, Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung, Mahmut Kandemir,

10th Annual Non-Volatile Memories Workshop -- Nominated as Memorable Paper Award

KCC Maximizing GPU Cache Utilization with Adjustable Cache Line Management

Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung,

Korean Computer Congress (KCC), 2019 -- Excellent Paper Award

2018

OSDI FlashShare: Punching Through Server Storage Stack from Kernel to Firmware for

Top Conference Ultra-Low Latency SSDs

Jie Zhang, Miryeong Kwon, Donghyun Gouk, Changlim Lee, Mohammad Alian, Myoungjun

Chun, Mahmut Kandemir, Nam Sung Kim, Jihong Kim, Myoungsoo Jung, 13th USENIX Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation

Amber: Enabling Precise Full-System Simulation with Detailed Modeling of All SSD

Top Conference Resources

MICRO

Donghyun Gouk, Miryeong Kwon, Jie Zhang, Sungjoon Koh, Wonil Choi, Nam Sung Kim,

Mahmut Kandemir, Myoungsoo Jung,

The 51st Annual IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture

TACO ReveNAND: A Fast-Drift Aware Resilient 3D NAND Flash Design

Top Journal Mustafa Shihab, **Jie Zhang**, Myoungsoo Jung, Mahmut Kandemir,

ACM Transactions on Architecture and Code Optimization (TACO), 2018

Eurosys FlashAbacus: A Self-governing Flash-based Accelerator for Low-power Systems

tel: +8619910031394|jiez@pku.edu.cn

Top Conference Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung,

The European Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys), 2018

IPDPS CIAO: Cache Interference-Aware Throughput-Oriented Architecture and Scheduling for

Major Conference GPUs

Jie Zhang, Shuwen Gao, Nam Sung Kim, Myoungsoo Jung,

32nd IEEE International Parallel & Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS), 2018

2017

CAL SimpleSSD: Modeling Solid State Drive for Holistic System Simulation

Major Journal Myoungsoo Jung, Jie Zhang, Ahmed Abulila, Miryeong Kwon, Narges Shahidi, John Shalf,

Nam Sung Kim and Mahmut Kandemir,

IEEE Computer Architecture Letters (CAL), 2017

IISWC Understanding System Characteristics of Online Erasure Coding on Scalable, Distributed

Major Conference and Large-Scale SSD Array Systems

Sungjoon Koh, Jie Zhang, Miryeong Kwon, Jungyeon Yoon, David Donofrio, Nam Sung Kim,

Myoungsoo Jung,

IEEE International Symposium on Workload Characterization (IISWC), 2017

IISWC TraceTracker: Hardware/Software Co-Evaluation for Large-Scale I/O Workload

Major Conference Reconstruction

Miryeong Kwon, Jie Zhang, Gyuyoung Park, Wonil Choi, David Donofrio, John Shalf,

Mahmut Kandemir, Myoungsoo Jung,

IEEE International Symposium on Workload Characterization (IISWC), 2017

NPC An In-depth Performance Analysis of Many-Integrated Core for Communication Efficient

Heterogeneous Computing

Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung,

IFIP International Conference on Network and Parallel Computing (NPC), 2017

IJPP Enabling Realistic Logical Device Interface and Driver for NVM Express Enabled Full

Major Journal System Simulations

Donghyun Gouk, Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung,

IFIP International Conference on Network and Parallel Computing (NPC) and Invited for

International Journal of Parallel Programming (IJPP), 2017

2016

HPCA DUANG: Fast and Lightweight Page Migration in Asymmetric Memory Systems

Top Conference Hao Wang, **Jie Zhang**, Gieseo Park, Sharmila Shridhar, Myoungsoo Jung, Nam Sung Kim,

IEEE Symposium on High Performance Computer Architecture (HPCA), 2016

tel: +8619910031394|jiez@pku.edu.cn

ASBD A Study for Block-level I/O Trace Reconstruction on All-Flash Arrays

Miryeong Kwon, Jie Zhang, Gyuyoung Park, Myoungsoo Jung,

Workshop on Architectures and Systems for Big Data (ASBD@ISCA), 2016

NVMSA An In-Depth Study of Next Generation Interface for Emerging Non-Volatile Memories

Major Conference Wonil Choi, Jie Zhang, Shuwen Gao, Jaesoo Lee, Myoungsoo Jung, Mahmut Kandemir,

IEEE Non-Volatile Memory Systems and Applications Symposium (NVMSA), 2016

INFLOW ROSS: A Design of Read-Oriented STT-MRAM Storage for Energy-Efficient Non-Uniform

Cache Architecture

Jie Zhang, Miryeong Kwon, Chanyoung Park, Myoungsoo Jung, Songkuk Kim,

USENIX Workshop on Interactions of NVM/Flash with Operating Systems and Workloads

INFLOW Couture: Tailoring STT-MRAM for Persistent Main Memory

Mustafa Shihab, Jie Zhang, Shuwen Gao, Josep Sloan, Myoungsoo Jung,

USENIX Workshop on Interactions of NVM/Flash with Operating Systems and Workloads

2015

ASBD CoDEN: A Hardware/Software CoDesign Emulation Platform for SSD-Accelerated Near

Data Processing

Jie Zhang, Damian Szmulewicz, Erick Macias, Myoungsoo Jung,

The 5th Workshop on Architecture and System for Big Data (ASBD), 2015

PACT NVMMU: Direct Solid State Disk Access for GPU-Accelerated Data Processing

Top Conference Jie Zhang, David Donofrio, John Shalf, Myoungsoo Jung,

The 24th International Conference on Parallel Architecture and Compilation Techniques

ICCD OpenNVM: An Open-Sourced FPGA-based NVM Controller for Low Level Memory

Major Conference Characterization

Jie Zhang, Gieseo Park, David Donofrio, Mustafa Shihab, John Shalf and Myoungsoo Jung,

The 33rd International Conference on Computer Design (ICCD), 2015

PACT-SRC Integrating 3D Resisteive Memory Cache into GPGPU for Energy-Efficient Data Processing

Jie Zhang, David Donofrio, John Shalf and Myoungsoo Jung,

International Conference on parallel Architecture and Compilation Techniques (PACT) -

ACM SRC 2nd Runner Award, 2015

FAST-WiP Shared Non-Volatile Mmeory Cache for Energy-Efficient High Throughput GPU Computing

Jie Zhang and Myoungsoo Jung,

USENIX Conference on File and Storage Technologies Working in Progress (FAST WiP), 2015

2014

HotStorage Power, Energy, and Thermal Considerations in SSD-Based I/O Acceleration

tel: +8619910031394|jiez@pku.edu.cn

Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung,

6th USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Storage and File Systems (HotStorage 14), 2014

PATENTS

- "Memory controlling device and computing device including the same", Myoungsoo Jung, Donghyun Gouk,
 Miryeong Kwon, Sungjoon Koh, Jie Zhang, America (US20190171566A1)
- "Flash-based accelerator and computing device including the same", Myoungsoo Jung, Jie Zhang, America (US10824341B2, US20180321859, US20170285968)
- "基于闪存的加速器和包含其的计算设备", Myoungsoo Jung, Jie Zhang, China (CN107291424)
- "基于闪存的加速器及包括该加速器的计算设备", Myoungsoo Jung, Jie Zhang, China (CN109460369)
- "Resistance switching memory-based accelerator", Myoungsoo Jung, Gyuyoung PARK, Jie Zhang, America (US20180321880A1)
- "PARALLEL PROCESSING UNIT, COMPUTING DEVICE INCLUDING THE SAME, AND THREAD SCHEDULING METHOD", Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung, America (WO2018021620)
- "MEMORY CONTROL APPARATUS AND COMPUTING DEVICE INCLUDING SAME", JUNG MYOUNGSOO, GOUK DONGHYUN, KWON MIRYEONG, KOH SUNGJOON, 정명수, JIE ZHANG, 국동현, 권미령, 고성준 장지에, Korea (KR1020180126267)
- "COMPUTING DEVICE, METHOD OF PROCESSING INPUT/OUTPUT REQUEST, AND RECORDING MEDIUM", Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung, Donghyun Gouk, Miryeong Kwon, Sungjoon Koh, America (pending)
- "FLASH-BASED COPROCESSOR", Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung, America (pending)
- "FLASH STORAGE DEVICE AND METHOD OF SCHEDULING PAGE VICTIMIZATION", Jie Zhang, Myoungsoo Jung, America (pending)

EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant, Computer Architecture and Memory System Lab

Sep 2013 – May 2021

- Cache and memory system optimization in GPGPU and multi-core system.
- Non-volatile memory (including Spin-transfer torque magnetic random-access memory and Phase Change Random Access Memory) characterization and optimization.
- Performance, power and thermal optimizations of Solid State Disk (SSD).

External Activities

Journal Paper Review/Sub-review

- IEEE Transactions on Computer
- ACM Transactions on Storage
- ACM Transactions on Architecture and Code Optimization
- ACM Transactions on Computer Systems
- IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems
- IEEE Computer Architecture Letters
- IEEE Transactions on Computer-Aided Design of Integrated Circuits and Systems

Conference Paper Review/Sub-review

- HPCA'24'18'16
- USENIX ATC'23
- ChinaSys'22
- SAC'22

tel: +8619910031394|jiez@pku.edu.cn

- HotStorage'20
- DAC'20 '19
- NVMSA'17 '16
- ICCD'19 '18 '17 '15
- IPDPS'18 '16
- DATE'19
- ASPLOS'19 '18 '17
- MICRO'18 '16

Invited Talks and Presentations

- Invited talk, "ZnG: Architecting GPU Multi-Processors with New Flash for Scalable Data Analysis", Intel Computational Storage Lab, 2020
- Presentation, "ZnG: Architecting GPU Multi-Processors with New Flash for Scalable Data Analysis", ISCA, online, 2020
- Presentation, "DRAM-less: Hardware Acceleration of Data Processing with New Memory", HPCA, San Diego, CA, 2020
- Presentation, "Scalable Parallel Flash Firmware for Many-core Architectures", FAST, Santa Clara, CA, 2020
- Presentation, "FUSE: Fusing STT-MRAM into GPUs to Alleviate Off-Chip Memory Access Overheads",
 HPCA, Washington DC, 2019
- Presentation, "FlashGPU: Placing New Flash Next to GPU Cores", DAC, Las Vegas, NV, 2019
- Presentation, "Maximizing GPU Cache Utilization with Adjustable Cache Line Management", Jeju, South Korea, 2019
- Presentation, "FlashShare: Punching Through Server Storage Stack from Kernel to Firmware for Ultra-Low Latency SSDs", Carlsbad, CA, 2018
- Presentation, "FlashAbacus: A Self-governing Flash-based Accelerator for Low-power Systems", Porto, Portugal, 2018
- Presentation, "CIAO: Cache Interference-Aware Throughput-Oriented Architecture and Scheduling for GPUs", IPDPS, Vancouver, Canada, 2018
- Presentation, "An In-depth Performance Analysis of Many-Integrated Core for Communication Efficient Heterogeneous Computing", NPC, Anhui, China, 2017
- Presentation, "ROSS: A Design of Read-Oriented STT-MRAM Storage for Energy-Efficient Non-Uniform Cache Architecture", Inflow, Savannah, GA, 2016
- Presentation, "Couture: Tailoring STT-MRAM for Persistent Main Memory", Inflow, Savannah, GA, 2016
- Presentation, "CoDEN: A Hardware/Software CoDesign Emulation Platform for SSD-Accelerated Near Data Processing", ASBD, Portland, OR, 2015
- Presentation, "NVMMU: Direct Solid State Disk Access for GPU-Accelerated Data Processing", PACT, San Francisco, CA, 2015
- Presentation, "Integrating 3D Resistive Memory Cache into GPGPU for Energy-Efficient Data Processing",
 PACT SRC, San Francisco, CA, 2015
- Presentation, "OpenNVM: An Open-Sourced FPGA-based NVM Controller for Low Level Memory Characterization", ICCD, New York city, NY, 2015
- Presentation, "Shared Non-Volatile Memory Cache for Energy-Efficient High Throughput GPU Computing", FAST WiP, Santa Clara, CA, 2015
- Presentation, "Power, Energy, and Thermal Considerations in SSD-Based I/O Acceleration", HotStorage, Philadelphia, PA, 2014

tel: +8619910031394 jiez@pku.edu.cn

Teaching Experience

- Computer Architecture (Fall'22)
- Introduction of Computer System (Fall'22)
- IIT 3002 Operating Systems (Fall'15, Fall'16)
- IIT 6036 Computer Organization and Design (Fall'15, Fall'16)
- IIT 7024 Advanced System Architecture (Spring'16)

Honors

- 2023: Intel Young Faculty Research Program
- 2022: ACM SIGCSE Rising Star Award
- 2021: Our storage-class memory research is selected as KAIST breakthrough 50 years
- 2020-2021: Korean BK21+ Scholarship
- 2020: HPCA travel grant
- 2019: Annual Non-Volatile Memories Workshop (NVMW) -- Nominated as Memorable Paper Award
- 2019: Korea Computer Congress (KCC) -- Best Presentation Paper Award
- 2018: OSDI travel grant
- 2015: ACM Student Research Competition 2nd Runner Award